Register of the Leonid Nikolaevich Kutukov Papers, 1898-1979
Hoover Institution Archives
Leonid Nikolaevich Kutukov Papers,
1898-1979
80195
Kutukov, Leonid Nikolaevich, 1897-
6 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (2.9 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, reports, clippings, and printed matter, relating to conditions in Russia and Russian military campaigns during World War I and the Russian Civil War, the Leib-Gvardii Moskovskii Polk and other Russian Imperial military units, and Russian emigre activities in France after the Civil War.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
Access Points
Russia. Armiia. Leib-gvardii moskovskii polk; Russians--France; World War, 1914-1918; World War, 1914-1918--Campaigns--Eastern; World War, 1914-1918--Russia; France; Russia; Soviet Union; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921; Parizhskii Vestnik
Biographical/Historical Note
Russian army officer, author and journalist.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of the papers of Leonid Kutukov, an officer in the Leib-Gvardii Moskovskii Polk (Moscow Life Guards Regiment) who emigrated to France after the Revolution and remained active in regimental activities abroad. The most important part consists of material related to the history of this regiment, especially during WWI and the Civil War. Of special interest are holograph and typescript eyewitness accounts by officers of the regiment re events during the early days of the revolution. This material was used by Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn in preparation for his multi-volume historical novel The Red Wheel. The collection contains a letter from the author to Leonid Kutukov in the WRITINGS FILE.
Also of interest is material related to right wing and monarchist circles in the emigration, including issues of Parizhskii Vestnik, published during the German occupation of Paris, 1942-1944.
Finally the collection contains the writings of Leonid Kutukov, mostly published in the journal Chasovoi, and miscellaneous material re the singing career of his wife, Sophia Kolomeitseva-Kutukova.
Series Description
- WRITINGS, 1934-1976. (Boxes 1-2)
  Bound notebooks of typescript drafts and clippings of writings by Leonid Kutukov about the Leib-Gvardii Moskovskii Polk during WWI, the Civil War, and emigration. Also includes a letter from Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn, articles on Russian history and politics, and miscellany re Russians on the Riviera. Arranged chronologically
- SUBJECT FILE, 1914-1973. (Boxes 2-3)
  Material re the Leib-Gvardii Moskovskii Polk, including reminiscences re WWI and the Civil War, lists and biographies of officers, and congratulatory messages to the regiment from members of the Imperial Family. Also includes miscellany re other guards regiments and monarchist printed matter. Arranged alphabetically by subject and therein by physical form
- SOPHIA KOLOMEITSEVA-KUTUKOVA FILE, 1927-1979. (Box 3)
  Consists mostly of bound notebook of photographs, programs, and clippings of reviews related to Sophia Kolomeitseva-Kutukova's career as an opera singer; and yearbook of Imperatorskoe Vospitatel'noe Obshchstvo Blagorodnykh Devits (Smol'nyi Institute). Arranged alphabetically by physical form
- PRINTED MATTER, 1907-1964. (Boxes 4-5)
  Mostly material re the history of Russian Imperial Guards regiments during WWI and the Civil War. Includes illustrated book re Russian Imperial military orders. Arranged chronologically
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1905-1970's. (Boxes 6-7)
  1 album depicting arrival of Russian forces in France during WWI, and 99 postcards and prints depicting the Sankt-Petersburgskaia Tretiia Klasicheskaia Gimnsziia, the Smol'nyi Institut (class of 1912), the grave of Gen. Nikolai Yudenich, Mikhail Tukhachevskii, and scenes of the the Riviera. Arranged by subject
- OVERSIZE FILE, 1898-1944. (Box7)
  Issues of Nov', 1898 and Parizhskii Vestnik, 1942-1944. Arranged alphabetically by title
Container List
- WRITINGS, 1934-1976.
  Bound notebooks
  - "Zapiski". Includes "Bunt v Zapasnom Batal'ene v Petrograde, 1917" and "Zagovor Belogo Mecha 1919", 1937. Typescript. Also includes letter from Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn, 1977 August, and printed copy of Khronika Odnogo Zagovora by A. Saparov" (Box 1., Folder 1)
  - Articles printed in various emigre publications, including Chasovoi, under the pseudonym of Nikolai Kremnev
    - "Rossiiskie mirazhi vo Frantsii I Italii", n.d. (Folder 2)
    - "Stat'i I ocherki", 1947-1976
      - Vol. I (Folder 3)
      - Vol. II (Folder 4)
    - "Kontury novogo stroia", 1958-1967 (Box 2., Folder 1)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1914-1973
  - Leib-Gvardii Izmailovskii Polk. Article in Chasovoi, 1930 September (Box 2., Folder 2)
  - Leib-Gvardii Moskovskii Polk
    - General
      - Archive and museum. Correspondence, 1965-1973 (Folder 3)
      - Ob'edinenie Leib-Gvardii Moskovskago Polka
        - Biulleten' Ob'edineniia Leib-Gvardii Moskovskago Polka, Nos. 68, 150-154, 1936-1961 (Folder 4)
        - "Polozhenie", 1950 August (Folder 5)
      - Tarnavka, Battle of
        - Congratulatory letters on the occasion of its 50th anniversary, 1964 (Folder 6)
        - Excerpts from German reports re battle, 1935 (Folder 7)
        - Issue of Biulleten', 1964 (Folder 8)
        - Reminiscences of participants, 1959-1964 (Folder 9)
    - Agreement between Lieut.-Gen. Nikolai Bredov and Polish Forces, 1920. Typescript copy (Folder 10)
    - Correspondence. Mostly congratulatory messages
      - General, 1930-1969 (Folder 11)
      - Andrei Vladimirovich, Grand Duke of Russia (Folder 12)
      - Mecklenburg-Strelitskii, Mikhail, Duke. Includes clippings of biography and obituary, 1927-1933 (Folder 13)
      - Nikolai Nikolaevich, Grand Duke of Russia, 1927 (Folder 14)
      - Ol'denburgskii, Aleksandr, Prince, 1929-1935 (Folder 15)
      - Vladimir Kirillovich, Grand Duke of Russia, 1963-1970 (Folder 16)
    - Excerpts from German reports re military action in which the regiment participated, 1915 (Folder 17)
    - Lists, biographies, and military service records of officers
      - General, 1914-1956 (Folder 18)
      - Dubrova, Nikolai, Col. Short biography (Folder 19)
      - Gal'fter, Victor, Maj.-Gen., Commander of Leib-Gvardii Moskovskii Polk. Military service record (Folder 20)
    - Writings about
      - General
        - "Leib-Gvardii Moskovskii Polk. K 150-letnemu iubileiu polka". Printed copy (Folder 21)
        - "Memuary o Zapasnom Batal'ene Leib-Gvardii Moskovskogo Polka, Do, Vo Vremia I Posle Bunta, 27 Fevralia 1917". Includes handwritten and typescript reminiscences by eyewitnesses (Folder 22-23)
        - "Poeziia Leib-Gvardii Moskovskago Polka". Handwritten, typescript, and printed copies (Folder 24)
        - "Vol'noopredeliaiushcheesia". Typescript (Folder 25)
      - Dubrova, Nikolai, Col.
        - "Boevoe Kreshchenie Leib-Gvardii Moskovskogo Polka v Velikuiu Voinu 1914 goda", n.d. Typescript (Folder 26)
        - "Istoriia Leib-Gvardii Moskovskogo Polka", excerpt from vol. 3, 1855-1878. Typescript. Includes postcard of Russian Memorial Church in Shipka, Bulgaria, and Chasovoi article re Bulgarian campaign, 1978 May-June (Folder 27)
        - "Prazdnovanie polkovogo prazdnika L-Gv. Moskovskago Polka v mirnoe vremia", n.d. Typescript (Folder 28)
      - Gal'fter, Victor, Maj.-Gen. Report re military action (battle at Fol'vark Zygmundov), 1914 September 7 (Folder 29)
      - Klimovich, Georgii, Col. (Box 3., Folder 1)
        - Untitled, n.d. Holograph
        - "Leib-Gvardii Moskovskii Polk v Velikuiu Voinu 1914-1917", 1934. Typescript
          - Notebook 1 (Folder 2)
          - Notebook 2 (Folder 3)
          - Notebook 3, "Prilozhenie" (Folder 4)
        - "Leib-Gvardii Moskovskii Polk v Grazhdanskuiu Voinu 1918-1920", 1934. Typescript (Notebook 4) (Folder 5)
  - Leib-Gvardii Pavlovskii Polk. Correspondence with Sergei Genriksen, 1965, and miscellany. See also PHOTOGRAPHS (Folder 6)
  - Monarchism. Miscellany re Grand Duke Vladimir Kirillovich and list of members of the Russian Imperial House, 1949 (Folder 7)
  - Parizhskii Vestnik. Account book, 1942-1944 (Folder 8)
  - Saksen-Al'tenburgskaia, Elena, Princess. Clipping of obituary, 1936 (Folder 9)
  - Tukhachevskii, Mikhail. Article about him in Chasovoi, 1966 March, and card with holograph signature, 1918. See also PHOTOGRAPHS (Folder 10)
- SOPHIA KOLOMEITSEVA-KUTUKOVA FILE, 1927-1979.
  See also PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Bound notebook of material related to Kolomeitseva-Kutukova's carreer as an opera singer. Includes programs, clippings of reviews, and portrait prints of the singer, 1927-1938 (Box 3., Folder 11)
  - Clippings, 1932-1979 (Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Folder 13)
  - Yearbook, I.V.O.B.D., (Imperatorskoe Vospitatel'noe Obshchstvo Blagorodnykh Devits, Smol'nyi Institut), 1905 (Folder 14)
- PRINTED MATTER, 1907-1964.
  See also OVERSIZE FILE
  - Sputnik Russkago na Riv'ere, 1907 (Box 4., Folder 1)
  - Rossiiskie Imperatorskie I Tsarskie Ordena, 1 910 (Folder 2)
  - Zhurnal Boevykh Deistvii 2-oi Gvardeiskoi Pekhotnoi Divizii, 1914, 1915 (Folder 3)
  - Materialy po istorii Gvardeiskoi pekhoty I artillerii v grazhdanskuiu voinu 1917-1922g., M. Goleevskii, 1937 (Folder 4)
  - Russkii Vremennik, No. 3, 1939 (Folder 5)
  - "Vestnik Gvardeiskago Ob"edineniia", 1951, 1964 (Folder 6)
  - La revolution russe de 1917, Jean Balensi and Paul Peronnet, 1960. Script for radio play (Box 5.)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1905-1970's.
  See also SOPHIA KOLOMEITSEVA-KUTUKOVA FILE
  - Album, Cherez Moria I Okeany. Illustrates voyage and arrival of Russian troops in France during WWI (Box 6., Folder 1)
  - 11 prints depicting Sophia Kolomeitseva-Kutukova (Folder 2)
  - 6 prints depicting uniforms and barracks of the Leib-Gvardii Pavlovskii Polk, 1 portrait print of Sergei Genriksen in uniform, n.d. (Folder 3)
  - 1 print of Mikhail Tukhachevskii, 1918 (Folder 4)
  - 1 print depicting the grave of Gen. Nikolai Yudenich, n.d. (Folder 5)
  - 7 prints related to Russian emigre life on the Riviera, n.d. (Folder 6)
  - 69 prints and postcards of tourist attractions on the Riviera, n.d. (Folder 7)
  - 2 group photographs depicting the Sankt-Petersburgskaia Tretiia Klasicheskaia Gimnsziia, 1913 (oversize) (Box 7., Oversize 1)
  - 1 group photograph depicting the Smol'nyi Institut class, 1912 (oversize) (Folder 2)
- OVERSIZE FILE, 1898-1944.
  Printed matter
  - Nov', 1898 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Parizhskii Vestnik, 1942-1944 (Folder 4)